So today's דף *Daf* is ס"א *Samech-Aleph*. We pick up in the
middle of ס' עמוד ב' *Samech Amud Beis*, however, רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda, אומר *Rebbi Yehuda Omer*. It is about oh, 15 lines before
the lines get wide. The line starts with the word קמח *Kemach*.
It actually says
קמח *Kemach* and then the word קמח *Kemach* right under it. So
it's the second קמח *Kemach*. I don't know if you see that.
Anyway, it's the middle of that line, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר
*Rebbi Yehuda Omer*. Okay, people with me? Yeah? All right. So רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר *Rebbi Yehuda Omer*. So we are in the
middle of a series of דרשות drashot. *Drashot* discussing how we know
that the wide range of מנחות Minchot *Menachot* that get הגשה Hagasha.
*Hagasha*. The תורה Torah *Torah* says explicitly that you take all of
the מנחות Minchot *Menachot* in the beginning of ויקרא Vayikra *Vayikra*, the
standard optional מנחה Mincha *Mincha*. It says if you bring any of
them, you give it to the כהן Kohen *Kohen*, והקריבה אל הכהן
והגישה אל המזבח V'hikrivah el hakohen v'higishah el hamizbe'ach. *Vihikrivah el hakohen
vihigishah el hamizbeach*. The כהן kohen *Kohen* brings it close to the
מזבח Mizbe'ach. *Mizbeach*, he touches it to the מזבח Mizbeach. *Mizbeach*. And
now we are a series of דרשות *Drashot* to learn from that
to include not just those מנחות Minchot *Menachot* but pretty much every
single one. Thank you. The one major debate is going to be
where we're going to see two exceptions. One exception is מנחת נסכים
minchat nesachim, *Minchat Nesachim* which is not coming because of itself, it's
coming because of the קרבן Korban *Korban*. And the other major debate
is going to be about a מנחת כהנים minchat kohanim *Minchat Kohanim*.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rebbi Shimon* says it's only a מנחה Mincha?
*Mincha* that there's a קמיצה Kmitza. *Kmitza* for, and רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda, *Rebbi Yehuda* says no, it's really for any מנחה Mincha. *Mincha*
of which a part goes on the מזבח Mizbeach *Mizbeach*. So you
need a part to go on the מזבח Mizbeach, *Mizbeach* to do
this הגשה Hagasha. *Hagasha*. If you want, you can think of the
הגשה Hagasha. *Hagasha* conceptually, I'm not saying it's exactly this, but you
can think of it conceptually as a type of זריקת הדם zrikat
hadam *Zrikas HaDam*. You know, now it's not really that because the
מנחה Mincha *Mincha* only becomes קדוש *Kadosh* once it's put on the
מזבח Mizbeach. *Mizbeach*, but that would allow there to be a greater
parallel between the מנחה Mincha *Mincha* and an animal קרבן Korban, *Korban*.
An animal קרבן korban *Korban* has a זריקת הדם zrikat hadam *Zrikas
HaDam* and a burning on the מזבח mizbe'ach. *Mizbeach*. So here too,
you would touch it to the מזבח mizbe'ach *Mizbeach* and then you
would burn it, although here the burning is what makes it valid,
not the touching to the מזבח mizbe'ach. *Mizbeach*. But it then also
fits why you only would do it with something which ultimately is
going to go to the מזבח mizbe'ach. *Mizbeach*. If none of the
מנחה Mincha, *Mincha* is going to go to the מזבח mizbe'ach, *Mizbeach*,
like for example by the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem, *Shtei Lechem* that
only the לבונה Levona *Levonah* goes to the מזבח mizbe'ach. *Mizbeach*, only
the כבשים Kvasim, *Kevasim* go to the מזבח mizbe'ach, *Mizbeach*, or the
לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim, *Lechem Hapanim* that only the לבונה Levona *Levonah*
goes to the מזבח mizbe'ach *Mizbeach*, in that case, since none of
it is getting burned, none of it you do הגשה Hagasha. *Hagasha*
to either. Okay, so we pick up in these series of דרשות
*Drashot* again. We are on ס' עמוד ב' *Samech Amud Beis*,
about 15 lines or so before the lines get wide. קמח *Kemach*,
תלמוד לומר Talmud Lomar והבאת *Talmud Lomer Vihiveisa*. Okay, so that's how
we learn to even a מנחת סוטה Minchat Sotah, *Minchat Sotah* you
do הגשה Hagasha. *Hagasha*. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר *Rebbi Yehuda Omer*,
והבאת *Vihiveisa*, you shall bring this מנחה Mincha. *Mincha*, לרבות מנחת סוטה
minchat sotah להגשה *Lirabos Minchas Sotah lihagasha*. So he learns it out
not from the word והקריבה *Vihikrivah*, which was רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
*Rebbi Shimon*, he learns it from the word והבאת *Vihiveisa*. You shall
bring it. Okay, וכן הוא אומר *Vichein hu omer*, and we see
that verb used by סוטה Sotah, *Sotah*, because it says והביא את
Es קרבנה עליה *Vihivei es korbanah aleha*, she shall bring her קרבן
korban *Korban* or he the husband shall bring the קרבן korban. *Korban*
for her. Anyway,
that's for סוטה Sotah, *Sotah*. So therefore you see that the מנחה
Mincha, *Mincha* of סוטה sota *Sotah* gets הגשה Hagasha. *Hagasha*. אבל מנחת
העומר Minchat Ha'omer, לא צריכה קרא *Aval Minchas Haomer lo tzrichah kra*.
But I don't need a קרא *Kra*. You, רבי שמעון Rebi Shimon
*Rebbi Shimon*, needed to use a פסוק Pasuk. *Pasuk* to teach you
that you do this for the מנחת העומר *Minchas Haomer*. I can
learn it out logically. I don't need a פסוק Pasuk? *Pasuk*. What?
Okay, well we'll see. You tell me if it's what you were
thinking. מאי טעמא *Mai Taama*? Why don't I need a פסוק Pasuk
*Pasuk*? מדינא קאתיא *Madina ka asya*. I can learn it out just
by like a logical derivation. מדינא
*Madina* here really means קל וחומר *Kal Vachomer*, but eventually it will
wind up to be more of a בנין אב *Binyan Av*. Let's
take a look. ומה מנחת חוטא Minchat Chotei שאינה טעונה תנופה Tnufa,
טעונה הגשה Hagasha *Umah Minchas Chotei she’eina te’unah tnupha te’unah hagasha*. We've
just got through proving based on פסוקים pesukim. *Psukim* that a מנחה
Mincha, *Mincha* for sin which does not have שמן shemen. *Shemen* and
לבונה levonah *Levonah*, that gets
and does not get waved, so it has like the minimum of
everything, the worst of everything, is it whatever nevertheless you do הגשה
Hagasha. *Hagasha*. So pretty much the logic should stand that any other
מנחה Mincha. *Mincha* you're certainly going to do הגשה Hagasha, *Hagasha* for.
ומה מנחת חוטא Minchat Chotei שאינה טעונה תנופה Tnufa טעונה הגשה Hagasha,
מנחת העומר שטעונה תנופה Tnufa אינו דין Din שטעונה הגשה Hagasha, *Umah
Minchas Chotei she’eina te’unah tnupha te’unah hagasha, Minchas Haomer shete’unah tnupha eino
din shete’unah hagasha*?
And that's exactly why it makes so much
sense.
Exactly what you would have said, right Michael? 100%. Absolutely wonderful. Okay,
so I'm also going to strike that down. What? No, no, let's
take a look.
Okay, so where were we? So ומה מנחת חוטא Minchat Chotei. שאינה
טעונה תנופה Tnufa, טעונה הגשה Hagasha. מנחת העומר שטעונה תנופה tnufah, *Umah
Minchas Chotei she’eina te’unah tnupha te’unah hagasha, Minchas Haomer shete’unah tnupha*. מנחת
העומר *Minchas Haomer* which is obviously more important. It gets waved. It
also gets שמן shemen *Shemen* and לבונה levonah *Levonah*. אינו דין שטעונה
הגשה Hagasha *Eino din shete’unah hagasha*? Certainly it should get הגשה Hagasha
*Hagasha*. So says wait, I'll make a difference. מה למנחת חוטא Chotei,
שכן באה חטים *Mah liminchas chotei shekein ba’ah chitin*. מנחת חוטא Minchat
Chotei. *Minchas Chotei* is in one way a little bit better than
the עומר Omer. *Omer*. It comes from wheat flour, not from barley
flour, which is the עומר Omer *Omer*. So maybe that because of
that,
that's why it gets הגשה Hagasha. *Hagasha*, but not עומר Omer *Omer*
which is less significant because it's only barley flour. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says מנחת סוטה minchat sotah תוכיח *Minchas Sotah tochiach*. Ah,
but the מנחת סוטה sotah. *Minchas Sotah*, that's only barley flour and
that gets הגשה Hagasha *Hagasha*. One minute. מה למנחת סוטה sotah שכן
באה לברר עון *Mah liminchas sotah shekein ba’ah livarer avon*. מנחת סוטה
sotah. *Minchas Sotah* has some importance in that it comes to play
the role of clarifying whether the woman has sin. Wait. Now that's
interesting because normally we've been emphasizing not the function that it's doing,
but the technical requirements, that if it has more technical requirements, why
higher technical requirement? Weighed wheat flour and so on, that makes us
assume that also more demands in terms of הגשה. hagashah. Here we're
saying that because of just the significance of its role, that it's
coming to clarify sin, that that explains why it gets this importance
of הגשה.
hagashah But מנחת חוטא Chotei doesn't clarify sin.
Well, that is true, actually. I mean, the תורה Torah, says מנחת
זכרון היא מנחת מזכרת עון, Minchat zikaron hi minchat mazkeres avon,
it actually says that it's that it causes the sin to be
remembered, but it's a good point. Right. Exactly. Right.
And if there was a sin or whatever, the clarification comes through,
right, the water. It's a very good point. What? I right. Meaning
it's related to that whole procedure. Michael's right, probably is the point.
Interesting question which I'm sure is answered, but I don't remember off
the top of my head, which is, let's say for some reason
the מנחה Mincha became פסול, Pasul, would you still be able to
do the procedure without the מנחה? Mincha, I by סוטה, I don't
know the answer off the top of my head if מעכב. Me'akev.
But yeah, it's true, it is certainly not No choice.
She has no choice. She has no choice to bring unless
she says unless she admits, but other than admitting, or there's the
question of if
she admitted, then she's not going to go through.
Right. Exactly. But she has no choice about the מנחה. Mincha. That's
true.
So, but like they have no choice. Right. You have no choice
to do it, but you're required, I think.
Any right,
there's many of personal obligatory sacrifices. Right. Here the problem is she
could know she's fully innocent and she has no choice.
Okay. So okay, so מנחת חוטא תוכיח. Minchat Chotei tochi'ach. Ah, so
מנחה Mincha, of a חוטא, that'll prove to you that that's not
the this specific role of clarifying sin, and nevertheless it gets הגשה.
hagashah וחזר הדין. Ve'chazar hadin. And you go back and forth. לא
ראי זה כראי זה ולא ראי זה כראי זה. Lo re'i zeh
kire'i zeh v'lo re'i zeh kire'i zeh. One distinctive characteristic is not
like the other. Right? One is it has distinctive because it's wheat;
the other's distinctive because it clarifies sin. But those are not in
the end important because those are not the הצד השוה שבהן. Hatzad
hashaveh shebahen. הצד השוה שבהן, Hatzad hashaveh shebahen,
the common denominator is, שכלם שוו לקמיצה. Shekulam shavu l'kmitza. Both of
them, this is again רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon, language, he emphasizes קמיצה.
Kmitza. That that you're doing קמיצה. Kmitza. ושוו להגשה. V'shavu l'hagasha. And
you do הגשה. hagashah? אף אני אביא מנחת העומר. Af ani avi
Minchat Ha'omer. So says רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda? I can therefore assume
that I would bring the עומר. Omer ששוו להם לקמיצה. Sheshavu lahem
l'kmitza. Since they do קמיצה. kmitzah תשוו להם להגשה. Tishvu lahem l'hagasha.
Now okay, nobody disagrees. Everybody agrees that the עומר Omer gets הגשה.
hagashah רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda just saying I don't need a פסוק.
Pasuk I can learn it out logically once I've established all these
other things get הגשה. hagashah.
What does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda?
use for what does he use with the extra part of the
פסוק? Pasuk So רש"י Rashi will get to that. So we'll get
back to that right now. ומה פרכת? U'mah parachta? And then you
don't have any question really to ask. So גמרא Gemara says one
minute, ורבי שמעון פרך הכי. V'Rabbi Shimon parach hachi. רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon's would challenge it. Here's what he would say: מה להצד השוה
שבהן, Mah l'hatzad hashaveh shebahen, even if you try to infer it
from מנחת חוטא and מנחת סוטה, I could say that they have
a common side שכן מצויין, Sheken metzuyan,
that they are common. Now, they're not really common, but they have
the possibility of being common. Meaning עומר Omer, is once a year,
beginning and end. All these other things could have be much more
frequent depending on how many times a person is doing these types
of sins, that or within כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, not one person,
you know, how much times women are being made into סוטות Sotot
and how many times people are doing the sins of a קרבן
עולה ויורד Korban Oleh V'yored that brings a מנחת חוטא. So therefore,
because they could be more frequent, that's why they demand הגשה. hagashah
Maybe we don't do הגשה hagashah. for a קרבן korban, that only
comes once a year. Okay, that's a pretty weak point, which is
the immediate response is, רבי יהודה, רבי יהודה would say back, אדרבה,
Adaraba, I'll say the opposite. המצוי טפי, Hamatzui tefei, the עומר Omer.
is more common. הני זימנין דלא משכחת להו כלל. Hani zimnin d'la
mishkachat lehu klal. At least an עומר Omer you know you're going
to get it once a year, right? These other things maybe you'll
never have, you'll go a year without ever having a סוטה, you'll
go a year without ever having a מנחת חוטא. So something coming
once a year, that's pretty significant even if it can't be more
than once a year. Okay, so that's just again more of an
academic debate whether we needed a פסוק Pasuk to tell you מנחת
העומר, you could have learned it out. Okay, now והביאתה. Ve'hevi'atah.
Now it goes on, והביאתה. Ve'hevi'atah.
Now, so we learned out from the word והביאתה Ve'hevi'atah to include
other מנחות Minchot, get הגשה. hagashah And now the ברייתא Braita is
saying maybe I should do something else with that word. Maybe it
says והביאתה Ve'hevi'atah אלא שיחיד מתנדב ומביא מנחה אחרת חוץ מאלו. Ela
she'yachid mitnadev u'mevi mincha acheret chutz me'eilu. Right?
So the פסוק pasuk, says והבאת את המנחה אשר יעשה מאלה לה'.
Ve'heiveta et hamincha asher ye'aseh me'eileh l'Hashem.
You shall bring from the מנחה Mincha. that you do from among
these, the personal מנחות Minchot that are mentioned in the beginning of
ויקרא Vayikra, to God. והקריבה אל הכהן והגישה vehigishah אל המזבח. He
gives it to the כהן kohen and he touches it to the
מזבח. mizbe'ach, So from והביאתה Ve'hevi'atah we learn it applies to more
מנחות Minchot. than are just mentioned here. But now the ברייתא Braita
is suggesting something radical. Maybe if the word והביאתה Ve'hevi'atah means it
applies to more מנחות, Minchot maybe what applies to more מנחות Minchos
is not that you do הגשה, hagashah? but actually if I take
a personal נדר Neder to bring a מנחה, Mincha, maybe I have
the option to make my own מנחה. Mincha, Maybe it doesn't have
to be the four five that the תורה, Torah you know, specify.
If that's what והביאתה Ve'hevi'atah is saying, other מנחות. Minchos So maybe
it doesn't mean other מנחות Minchos like חוטא and עומר, Omer maybe
it means I
can... Maybe that's what it means.
Where are we? והבאת אל ה' אשר יקריב ממנה מנחה אחרת חוץ
מאלו שבענין Veheveisa el Hashem asher yakriv mimena mincha acheres chutz me'elu
shebe'inyan other than those that are mentioned in this context right here
in the Torah as a דין I could have logically made that
argument. How is that? ציבור מביא מנחה מן החיטים חובה ומביא מנחה
מן השעורים חובה. Tzibur meivi mincha min hachitim chova umeivi mincha min
hase'orim chova. The ציבור Tzibur brings an obligatory wheat flour מנחה, Mincha,
the שתי הלחם, Shtei HaLechem. and an obligatory barley flour מנחה, Mincha
the עומר. Omer. That's nice, right? Those are the two bookends, the
two obligatory מנחות Minchos? of the ציבור, Tzibur, the עומר Omer and
the שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem So אף יחיד לביא מנחה מן החיטים
נדבה Af yachid lavi mincha min hachitim nedava so when the Torah
introduces that as a private citizen, that is a personal as a
personal קרבן, korban. in the beginning of ויקרא, Vayikra I can bring
a free-will מנחה. Mincha. What type of free-will מנחה Mincha do I
bring? Out of flour out of wheat flour. That's what the Torah
says. So maybe in parallel to what the ציבור Tzibur does by
obligatory, they have a wheat flour obligatory and a barley flour obligatory,
maybe I have a wheat flour optional מנחה, Mincha I can also
bring a barley flour optional מנחה. Mincha
So therefore, so יביא מנחה מן השעורים נדבה Yavi mincha min hase'orim
nedava maybe I have the option to bring a barley flour one
as a נדבה. Nedava. So תלמוד לומר Talmud Lomar the verse teaches
אלה. Eleh. It says and only these. אין לי אלא אלה, Ein
li ella eleh, only these. So even though we're including other מנחות
Minchos for הגשה, hagasha.
only when it comes to your מנחת נדבה, Minchas Nedava, it's only
the ones the Torah mentions. אין לי אלא אלה. Ein li ella
eleh. או אינו אומר אלה אלא לומר הרי עלי מנחה שמביא חמשתן.
O eino omer eleh ella lomar harei alay mincha shemeivi chameshtan. Maybe
it's saying these to say all of these, that if you say
that I'm going to bring a מנחה, Mincha, so if you say
I'm going to bring a מאפה תנור, Maafeh Tanur, you bring a
מאפה תנור. Maafeh Tanur. If I'm going to bring סולת, Soles, you
bring סולת. Soles. But let's say somebody just says, "I'm going to
bring a מנחה." Mincha Maybe he has to bring all of the
five. Maybe he doesn't have an option for the way we say
that if you just say generically מנחה, Mincha you have to bring
one of them. Maybe if you say "I'm going to bring a
מנחה," Mincha you have to bring all of
them? שמביא חמשתן. Shemeivi chameshtan. תלמוד לומר Talmud Lomar מאלה, Me'eleh, from
these. רצה אחת מביא רצה חמישה מביא. Ratza achas meivi ratza chamisha
meivi. If you just say generically, "I'm going to bring a מנחה,"
Mincha you have a choice. You can bring any one of those
types of מנחה mincha or if you want, go ahead, bring five
types of מנחה. mincha Okay, anyways that's just saying that the פסוק
pasuk is not just telling you about הגשה, hagasha we also learn
from the פסוק pasuk that your only options as a מנחת נדבה
Minchas Nedava are the ones mentioned in the Torah. Okay, רבי שמעון
אומר, Rebi Shimon Omer, now we are going to get closer to
the debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. and the חכמים Chachamim about
whether what's the story with מנחת כוהנים? Minchas Kohanim? Let's take a
look. רבי שמעון אומר Rebi Shimon Omer את המנחה. Es haMincha. It
says והבאת את המנחה. Veheveisa es hamincha. זו המנחה. Zo hamincha. So
את is an extra word, it seems to like also include even
more. So לרבות שאר מנחות Lerabos shaar minchos to include even other
מנחות Minchos, get הגשה. hagasha, What are the other מנחות? Minchos What
haven't we mentioned? We certainly have mentioned a lot. So it's going
to tell you כגון מנחת נכרים מנחת נשים להגשה. Kegon minchas nochrim
minchas nashim lehagasha. Like women and non-Jews. Again, the issue about why
women is mentioned is very curious because there's no different status to
the מנחה mincha of women. We will see in the next משנה
Mishna when it comes to תנופה, tnufah, there's a discussion whether women
do תנופה tnufah, the same way there's a discussion whether women do
סמיכה. Smicha. But a standard מנחה mincha. you don't do תנופה tnufah,
with. And a standard מנחה mincha, the Torah never designates men versus
women. There's no Halachic difference. But somehow they're always keep getting thrown
in. As I said, either it's to tell you here it's not
different. If there's a difference it'll be by תנופה, tnufah it won't
be by a standard מנחה, mincha or as I said before, you
know the list of all the מנחות Minchos that you do this
for הגשה hagasha, comes out to a perfect ten, so I have
a suspicion they're just throwing in women to get to the ten.
Actually if you look at the side in the שיטה מקובצת Shita
Mekubetzas ד, Daled, he says תיבת כגון מנחת נכרים מנחת נשים תימחק.
Teivas kegon minchas nochrim minchas nashim timachek. That that כגון Kegon might
have been a later gloss. It might have just said לרבות שאר
מנחות. Lerabos shaar minchos. So maybe it was just talking about non-Jews
but some person who put in the gloss put in, you know,
women and non-Jews. Okay. יכול שאני מרבה אף שתי הלחם ולחם הפנים.
Yachol she'ani marbeh af shtei halechem ulechem hapanim. Maybe I would include
even the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem and לחם הפנים, Lechem HaPanim that
maybe you do הגשה hagasha, there. The reason we know you don't
is because those no part of the מנחה mincha itself put on
the מזבח. mizbe'ach The שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem you do the animals,
the כבשים, kevasim the blood is thrown on the מזבח mizbe'ach? and
the לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim? you do the little things of לבונה
levonah that are on the שולחן, Shulchan, you put them on the
מזבח, mizbe'ach but no part of the מנחה mincha? is itself put
on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. But I haven't said that yet. So maybe
even those get
הגשה. hagasha? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar, מאלה. Me'eleh. From among these. Not
all מנחות, menachot only some of them. ומה ראית לרבות שאר מנחות
ולהוציא שתי הלחם ולחם הפנים. Uma raisa lerabos shaar minchos ulehotzi shtei
halechem ulechem hapanim. Why did you include all other מנחות menachot for
הגשה hagasha, and not the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem and לחם הפנים?
Lechem HaPanim מרבה אני שאר מנחות שיש מהם לאישים. Marbeh ani shaar
minchos sheyesh mehem le'ishim. So this is what I've been saying. I
would include other מנחות menachot that some of the מנחה mincha actually
goes on the fire. ומוציא אני שתי הלחם ולחם הפנים שאין מהם
לאישים. Umotzi ani shtei halechem ulechem hapanim she'ein mehem le'ishim. To exclude
the שתי הלחם shtei halechem, and לחם הפנים lechem hapanim, that none
of it goes on the fire. Other things are on the fire,
the לבונה levonah or whatnot, but the מנחה mincha itself does not
go on the fire. Now so that's how to exclude those two.
One criteria is something has to go on the fire. Now there's
another thing we have to exclude, which is מנחת נסכים, minchat nesachim,
which all goes on the fire, but also there's no הגשה. hagasha
והלא מנחת נסכים כולה לאישים. v'halo minchat nesachim kullah l'ishim. One minute,
you burn the מנחת נסכים, minchat nesachim the מנחה mincha that comes
with an עולה olah and a שלמים, shelamim, you burn it all
on the fire. יכול טעונה הגשה? yachol te'unah hagashah? Maybe you'd הגשה
hagasha. on it? תלמוד לומר והקריבה. talmud lomar v'hikrivah. You shall bring
it, only it and not something else. והא אפיקתיה? v'ha apikteih? But
you've learned the word והקריב v'hikriv to tell you something else, to
include like מנחת סוטה and other things? So the דרשה drasha here
is והקריב והקריבה. v'hikriv v'hikrivah. The ה, hei, you shall bring it,
the מפיק ה mapik hei means only it, so don't make your
category too large. So again the question is, okay, but who's telling
you what to include, what to exclude? Obviously we're coming with a
certain model about what makes sense that requires הגשה hagasha and what
does not. ומה ראית לרבות שאר מנחות ולהוציא מנחת נסכים? u'mah ra'ita
l'rabot she'ar menachot u'l'hotzi minchat nesachim? Why do you include other מנחות
menachot and exclude מנחת נסכים minchat nesachim from הגשה? hagasha. דף ס'
עמוד א', Daf Samech Amud Aleph, up now of ס' עמוד א'.
Samech Amud Aleph. מרבה אני שאר מנחות. marbeh ani she'ar menachot. I
include other מנחות menachot, שבאות בגלל עצמן. sheba'ot biglal atzman. They come
for their own accord. Any normal מנחה mincha you're bringing because of
the obligation to bring the מנחה mincha or your desire to bring
a מנחה. Mincha, ומוציא אני את מנחת נסכים שאינה באה בגלל עצמה.
u'motzi ani et minchat nesachim she'eina ba'ah biglal atzmah. I exclude the
מנחת נסכים minchat nesachim, that's not coming because of it itself. It's
coming because you obligated yourself to bring a קרבן korban, or the
ציבור tzibur brings a קרבן korban, and this is שלעפט shlepped along,
this comes to accompany the קרבן. korban So something that's accompanying, not
itself seen as the object of הקרבה, hakravah, does not get the
הגשה hagasha. to the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So again all of these two
basic criteria make sense, as I said. One is, if it's seen
as part of the הקרבה hakravah of the קרבן, korban that's only
when you're focusing on being מקריב makriv this. If the focus is
you're מקריב, makriv, let's say the מנחת נסכים, minchat nesachim you're מקריב
makriv the animal, and then after you מקריב makriv the animal, what
do you do with it? You burn the אימורים eimurim on the
מזבח mizbe'ach, and you burn the מנחת נסכים minchat nesachim on the
מזבח. mizbe'ach, So it's not like you're really being מקריב makriv the
מנחה, Mincha you're being מקריב makriv the animal and then this is
part of the animal and part of what gets done, you burn
it on the מזבח. mizbe'ach, So that makes sense you don't do
הגשה. hagasha, The other issue about when you are bringing it but
it itself is not going on the מזבח, mizbe'ach like the שתי
הלחם, shtei halechem, like the לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, let's take that
as the clearer example where the לבונה levonah goes on the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. So there, nevertheless, I think the idea is, is that when
it itself is going on the מזבח, mizbeach, then you sort of
do this, in my mind sort of the model here is, is
that it's sort of like a, you know, a quasi זריקת הדם
zrikat hadam and then you have the burning. Like you have the
זריקת הדם zrikat hadam, and אימורים. eimurim. So you have this הגשה
hagashah, to the מזבח mizbeach. and then you have the burning of
the rest. If this none of this is being burnt on the
מזבח, mizbeach. you don't do it. Now that could be questioned because
you could say wait a minute, you know, actually maybe it makes
a lot of sense. Maybe the לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, you know,
the זריקת הדם zrikat hadam. and the burning of the אימורים eimurim
are two separate objects. So maybe by the case of the לחם
הפנים, lechem hapanim, right, why don't we say the לבונה gets put
on the מזבח mizbeach, and the מנחה Mincha gets touched to the
מזבח? mizbeach. You know, if that's the sort of model I'm working
with, right, the touching is like a זריקת הדם, zrikat ha-dam, why
do you need the actual מנחה Mincha. itself to be burnt? Right,
the רבונו של עולם Ribbono Shel Olam question, by the שתי הלחם,
Shtei HaLechem by לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim. what do you do? You
burn the לבונה and the כהנים kohanim eat the לחם הפנים. Lechem
HaPanim, Why don't we say, okay, burn the לבונה and touch the
מנחה? Mincha What's problematic with that? That makes sense. So it seems
like maybe we're saying more than just my idea or different than
my idea of this parallel to זריקת הדם. zrikat ha-dam, It seems
that what we're saying is that the touching to the מזבח mizbeach.
might be the final הקדשה, hakdashah, the final sanctification of the מנחה
Mincha, that allows it to be put on the מזבח. mizbeach, And
this is an interesting idea by מנחות menachot, that we have in
contrast to animal קרבנות. korbanot. By animal קרבנות korbanot there's an assumption
that they basically have the full קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf from the
moment you sanctify it that allow it to be put on the
מזבח. mizbeach Maybe the שחיטה shechitah adds a final level of קדושת
הגוף, kedushat haguf, but there's not so much a focus on the
need of the כלי kli to sanctify it. The מנחה Mincha is
very different. The מנחה Mincha is something you construct. And therefore, for
some reason, even though I sanctify the flour and I sanctify the
oil, as we've seen before now and continue to see, it doesn't
really get full קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf until you put it in
a כלי שרת kli sharet and you mix it and so on
and so forth. So understanding the need to imbue it with sanctity,
maybe that's the understanding that in order what will entitle you to
be מקריב makriv this on the מזבח, mizbeach to give it that
fullest level of sanctity, you require the הגשה. hagashah And therefore, if
none of it is going on the מזבח, mizbeach it's not required.
Okay, so that's an interesting other exception, not going on the מזבח,
mizbeach. no הגשה hagasha is required. Okay, so we have those two
exceptions, not going on the מזבח mizbeach. and the case of מנחת
נסכים Minchat Nesachim which is not coming for its own sake. And
now we have the issue that is debated, if it all is
being burnt on the מזבח. mizbeach. Let's take a look. סוף Sof
line once on the top of ס' עמוד א'. Samech Amud Aleph.
והלא, V'halo, how about מנחת כהנים kohanim ומנחת כהן משיח, u'minchat kohen
mashiach, the מנחה Mincha of כהנים kohanim and the מנחה Mincha of
the כהן גדול kohen gadol which is brought every day, half in
the morning, half in the evening. באות בגלל עצמן, ba'ot biglal atzman,
they come on their own accord, they're not coming, you know, being
שלעפט shlepped along with something else. יכול יהיו טעונות הגשה? yachol yihyu
te'unot hagashah? Maybe those get הגשה? hagasha Right, why not? תלמוד לומר
והגישה. talmud lomar v'higishah. So והגישה vehigishah?
with the מפיק ה, mapik heh, you shall touch it, only it
and not something else. גמרא gemara, says האי מיבעי ליה לגופא hai
mibei lei legufa שתעונה הגשה. sheteunah hagasha. Now what do you mean
that you can't learn something from the word והגישה? That's the keyword,
that's telling you you do הגשה. hagasha. How can you learn anything
else from it? So it says no, מן והגיש והגישה, min vehigish
vehigishah, it could have said והגיש, vehigish, you touch. Why does it
say you touch it? That again, the ה heh indicates only this
and not something else. Something else is going to be excluded. All
right, but what is making you choose to exclude מנחת כוהנים? Minchat
Kohanim? What makes it different? ומה ראית לרבות שאר מנחות ולהוציא מנחת
כוהנים? u-mah ra’ita lerabot she’ar menachot u-lehotzi minchat kohanim? What makes you
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon because by the way, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon,
position is debated, but this is at least this is going according
to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon What makes רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon include
all other מנחות menachot. but exclude the מנחת כוהנים Minchat Kohanim from
הגשה hagasha and מנחת כוהן משיח? Minchat Kohen Mashiach? מרבה אני שאר
מנחות, marbeh ani she’ar menachot, I include other מנחות, menachot, שיש מהם
לאישים, she-yesh meihem le-ishim, some of it goes on the fire, ובאות
בגלל עצמן, u-ba'ot biglal atzman, and they come for their own accord,
and here's the third point, ויש מהם לכוהנים. ve-yesh meihem la-kohanim. Some
goes on the fire, but the rest is eaten by the כוהנים.
kohanim. That's every standard מנחה, Mincha. with the exception of a מנחת
כוהן Minchat Kohen which fully gets burnt. ומוציא אני שתי הלחם ולחם
הפנים, u-motzi ani shtei ha-lechem ve-lechem ha-panim, I'll exclude the שתי הלחם
shtei halechem and לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim שאין מהם לאישים. she-ein meihem
le-ishim. No part of the מנחה mincha goes to the fire, only
the לבונה goes to the fire, no part of the מנחה mincha
goes to the fire or the כבשים kvashim goes to the fire,
but again, not the מנחה. mincha ומנחת נסכים, u-minchat nesachim, I'll exclude
and מנחת נסכים Minchat Nesachim שאינה באה בגלל עצמה, she-einah ba'ah biglal
atzmah, to exclude מנחת נסכים minchat nesachim that although it goes on
the fire, it's not coming on its own accord, it's only coming
because of the animal קרבן. korban, And ומנחת כוהנים ומנחת כוהן משיח,
u-minchat kohanim u-minchat kohen mashiach, and I'll exclude these two שאין מהם
לכוהנים, she-ein meihem la-kohanim, no, the כוהנים kohanim do not get any
part of it. So this is the position of רבי שמעון, although
it's interesting this ברייתא braita does not discuss רבי יהודה'ס Rabbi Yehuda's
opposing opinion, or the תנא קמא'ס Tanna Kamma's opposing opinion, but basically
it's what do you buy into this third criteria? Everybody agrees what
do you need to do הגשה, hagasha. it has to come on
its own accord, it has to be the מנחה minchah itself but
get burnt on the מזבח, mizbeach. some of the מנחה, mincha but
רבי שמעון has a third criteria, the remainder of it has to
be eaten by the כוהנים, kohanim, not that it's all burnt on
the מזבח. mizbe'ach Okay, I do not know, it's hard for me
to understand
conceptually why that should be true, right? Again, if you think about
what we have models of that, like an עולה, olah, whatever, things
that are fully burnt on the מזבח. mizbe'ach, However you understand the
point of הגשה, hagasha whether it's what I was suggesting, that it's
a type of a זריקת הדם, zrikas hadam whether you understand it's
a fuller sanctification of the object itself that lets you be מקריב
makriv it on the מזבח, mizbe'ach. it's hard to understand conceptually why
you wouldn't do it if it's all getting burnt as opposed to
some is getting burnt and some is getting eaten. I really don't
have a good explanation, but that's what he says, that's another criteria
he has. So now we've just end the דרשות.
והרים, ve-herim, this is the end of that פסוק, pasuk it says
you bring it to the כוהן kohen and he touches it to
the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So now we're done with הגשה, hagashah, we're just
going to make a דרש drash on the end of the פסוק
pasuk that says the כוהן kohen takes the קמיצה kmitzah and puts
it on the מזבח. mizbe'ach, He shall lift up, יכול בכלי, yachol
bicheli, maybe he can take the קמיצה kmitzah? with a vessel, maybe
he doesn't have to use his hand to do the קמיצה? kmitzah,
תלמוד לומר והרים ממנו בקומצו. talmud lomar ve-herim mimenu be-kumtzo. It says
in another פסוק pasuk that he shall lift up from his hand
breast, so you see the word הרמה haramah means with your hand
itself. מה הרמה האמורה להלן בקומצו, mah haramah ha-amurah le-hallan be-kumtzo, the
same way over there in צו Tzav it's talking about his own
hand, אף הרמה האמורה כאן בויקרא בקומצו, af haramah ha-amurah kan be-Vayikra
be-kumtzo, here in ויקרא in his own hand breast. Okay, so that
was just about the act of קמיצה, but what we see is
what requires הגשה? hagashah Anything that's coming for its own accord, that
part of it goes on the מזבח, mizbe'ach and then the debate
is do you need some of it on the מזבח mizbe'ach and
some for the כוהנים, kohanim, or even if all of it is
going on the מזבח mizbe'ach like the מנחת כוהנים. Minchat Kohanim. And
again, it's hard for me to understand exactly why to exclude מנחת
כוהנים. Minchat Kohanim. It's hard in general to understand the purpose of
הגשה, hagashah. but I suggested two things, I think very conceptually distinct
ideas. One to see it as part of the act of הקרבה
hakravah itself, a type of a quasi זריקת הדם, zrikas hadam something
is touching the מזבח mizbe'ach, before it gets burnt on the מזבח.
Mizbe'ach And the other to see it as a type of a
הכשרה, hachsharah, sanctification, which allows you then to finally bring it to
the מזבח. Mizbe'ach Okay, now we go onto, we move away from
specifically מנחות, menachot and we look at תנופה, tnufah, because the משנה
Mishnah said something gets הגשה hagashah and תנופה, tnufah something's only תנופה,
tnufah something both. So a standard מנחה mincha, does not get תנופה,
tnufah and now we're going to look at the things that do
get תנופה tnufah with or without הגשה. hagashah So with or without
הגשה we're not even going to limit ourselves to מנחות. menachos, There's
a number of things in the תורה Torah that get תנופה, tnufah?
and now we're going to look at them. אלו טעונות תנופה, elu
teunot tnufah,
the following things get waved, ואין טעונות הגשה, ve-ein teunot hagasha, without
הגשה. So already we're not going to include certain מנחות, menachot like
the עומר Omer, by the way I'll just say, is an example
of you both do תנופה tnufah, it says in the תורה torah
and it's a מנחה mincha. and we just finished with the דרשה
drashah as a standard מנחה mincha gets הגשה. Okay, but most things
are not. A standard מנחה mincha doesn't get תנופה tnufah. and a
standard thing that does get תנופה tnufa isn't a מנחה. mincha So
that's basically what this list is. Things that get תנופה tnufa without
הגשה, mostly it will be non-מנחות minchot that we're going to discuss.
So what do you do with it? You wave them.
Yeah. So we're going to discuss the actual procedure. We'll touch on
it today, it'll be more tomorrow, but basically it says you go
back and forth and up and down. Okay.
And then go near the מזבח.
Mizbe'ach, And well we'll see, depends on what they are. Some things
do. Let's take a look at the list. Okay? So it says
like this: לוג שמן של מצורע ואשמו log shemen shel metzora veashamo
because the מצורע metzora in his purification process brings an אשם asham
and a לוג log of oil and they wave and it says
that the כהן kohen waves it and then you use this לוג
log of oil to put on his ear and whatever, you know,
to do the whole process here. We'll read the פסוקים. psukim, וזאת
תורת
המצורע ביום טהרתו והובא אל הכהן.
vezot torat
hametzora beyom taharato vehuva el hakohen.
So it says, so first you do the thing on day seven
with the birds and then he's whatever, ויהי ביום השביעי יגלח את
כל שערו וביום השמיני יקח שני כבשים תמימים. vayehi bayom hashvii yegaleach
et kol searo uvayom hashemini yikach shnei kvasim tmimim.
Then on day eight what do you do? I'm sorry, the birds
thing is before seven days. You first do the birds, then you
wait, then you do then seven days you shave, eighth day you
do the final process. וכבשה אחת בת שנתה תמימה ושלושה עשרונים סולת
מנחה בלולה בשמן ולוג אחד שמן. vecheves achas bas shnata tmima ushlosha
esronim solet mincha blula vashemen velog echad shamen.
So you take these sheep and a לוג log of שמן. והעמיד
הכהן המטהר את האיש המטהר ואתם לפני השם פתח אהל מועד ולקח
הכהן את הכבש האחד. vehemid hakohen hametaher es haish hametaher veosam lifnei
hashem pesach ohel moed velakach hakohen es hacheves haechad. One of the
lambs. והקריב אותו לאשם. vehekriv oso leasham. That's going to be an
אשם. asham. ואת לוג השמן והניף אותם תנופה לפני השם. ve es
log hashemen vehanif osam tnufa lifnei hashem.
You wave it as a wave offering before God. Then ושחט את
הכבש. veshachat es hacheves. You slaughter the lamb. So you wave it
notice when the lamb is still alive. Okay. And then you slaughter
the lamb. במקום אשר ישחט את החטאת ואת העולה במקום הקודש כי
כחטאת האשם. bimkom asher yishchat es hachatas ve es haola bimkom hakodesh
ki kachatas haasham. And then you take from the blood of the
אשם asham and you take from the oil and you put it
on, you know, his ear and his thumb and and so on
and so on. That's part of the purification process. Okay? So this
אשם asham with the לוג log are going to be used to
be מטהר metaher him. The אשם asham is brought as a קרבן,
korban the blood is נזרק, nizrak, the לוג log is not exactly
brought as a קרבן, korban it's brought together though with the אשם
asham in order to allow you to purify the מצורע metzora and
they're waved together when they are both alive. So to some degree,
conceptually the waving is presumably designating them, you know, as the objects
to be מטהר metaher the מצורע. metzora. Somehow sanctifying, designating, setting you
know so now they have been have this process that allows the
אשם asham through bringing it as a קרבן korban and using its
blood to be part to work in the process for the מצורע
metzora as well as for the oil.
How quick. Yeah. How can you wave a lamb and a לוג
שמן log shemen at the same time with your two a live
lamb?
Well that's why they that's why they made handles for it. I
mean if you get you can get the לוג log of שמן
just in your pinky or something.
You know a לוג log is a measurement.
Yeah, but you get it you have it in a כלי. kli.
I mean you don't have oil.
How can you hold it with a live lamb?
That's what I said, that's what they have handles for. You ever
try juggling like three bags of grocery?
Oh, but did you ever pick up a live animal?
Right, picking.
Well we're going to see in the גמרא, gemara we're going to
see in the גמרא Gemara it's going to say that you could
do them separately, בדיעבד bedieved you're יוצא yotzei if you do separately.
But I don't think it's I don't know, I mean you know
I'm serious if you got your arms through a handle or something
is it so while you're
holding a whole lamb.
How big of a lamb?
Like a 30 pound well.
All right.
Okay, I don't know, I haven't tried. Okay. Okay, so let's take
a look. לוג שמן של מצורע ואשמו, log shemen shel metzora veashamo,
so the לוג log of oil with the אשם. asham. והביכורים כדברי
רבי אלעזר בן יעקב. vehabikkurim kidvrei Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov. The ביכורים
bikkurim according to רבי אלעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov. What
the תורה Torah says with the ביכורים bikkurim it says you shall
bring it before the כהן kohen, and you shall והנחתו לפני מזבח
השם אלוקיך. vehinachto lifnei mizbeach hashem elokecha.
You shall place it down in front of the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. וענית
ואמרת ארמי אובד אבי veanita veamarta arami oved avi etc., you know,
and it says and then the כהן kohen takes it והניחו לפני
השם veheynicho lifnei hashem והניחו לפני השם. veheynicho lifnei hashem.
So it says twice you place it, it never says you wave
it, okay, but there's a positions תנאים tannaim that understand this placing
actually means waving. So one of those positions is רבי אלעזר בן
יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov in the משנה mishna in סוטה and
here he's being alluded to. By the way, that's interesting because scholars
often assume that some of these like composite, you know, like lists,
I mean composite the wrong word anyway, lists are maybe very early.
Like here's like you know the אין בין. ein bein. Here's all
the things between יום כיפור yom kippur and שבת shabbat and אין
בין ein bein this that and אין בין ein bein this that.
Although it sort of you know goes through ש"ס shas but they're
all sort of pulled together through this like theme of אין בין.
ein bein. Like we had it earlier in מנחות, we had you
know these are the things that are מעכבין זה את זה, meakvin
zeh es zeh, these are the things that are not מעכבין זה
את זה meakvin zeh es zeh and you know don't limit yourself
you know to קרבנות, korbanot, you go to תפילין tfillin and מזוזה
mezuzah and whatnot. So there's an interesting question whether those were some
of the early compilations of משניות, mishnayot, you know before you have
them like schematically organized you might have them organized around these things
of אין בין ein bein this with this, אלו דברים שאין מעכבין
זה את זה elu devarim sheein meakvin zeh es zeh etc., or
were they sort of like were they synthesized once those original statements
had maybe been said a lot in their original place and they
were sort of picked and brought together and synthesized. into this type
of a משנה. mishna. So here at least, the fact that it's
making reference, it doesn't say דברי רבי אליעזר בן יעקב divrei Rebbe
Eliezer ben Yaakov or רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר, Rebbe Eliezer ben
Yaakov omer, כדברי רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Ki-divrei Rebbe Eliezer ben Yaakov
reflects the fact that that debate was already known, רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב Rebbe Eliezer ben Yaakov had said his opinion somewhere else, and
here it's being referred to. So it seems like at least this
משנה mishna right is in—no, but it also is later than the
where those statements were maybe originally said. Okay, so anyway, so because
according to רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rebbe Eliezer ben Yaakov now, which
is not clear in the פסוקים, psukim. ואימורי שלמי יחיד בחזה ושוק
שלהן. v'imurei shalmei yachid b'chazeh v'shok shelahen.
That's clear in the פסוקים. psukim That the Torah says what do
you do when you bring a שלמים? shlamim? It says you shall
take את חזה התנופה ואת שוק התרומה על אישי החלבים יביאו להניף
תנופה לפני השם. et chazeh hatnufah v'et shok hatrumah al ishei hachalavim
yavi'u l'hanif tnufah lifnei Hashem.
Bring the side of the and the and the breast and you
put it together with the fat and you wave it, and then
what you do is the fats go on the מזבח Mizbe'ach, and
the כהנים kohanim get the חזה chazeh and the שוק. shok. Okay,
so there it's very explicit in the פסוקים psukim that that's what
you do with a שלמים. shlamim. That seems to be a little
different, very different from the idea of like with all these things
you could say what's the significance of תנופה? tnufa. But נזיר nazir
seems very much to be to sanctify and designating it to be
used in the ritual, but the שלמים shlamim it's a way of
giving it to God. And I would say that the argument and
that way of—the reason to wave with the חזה התנופה chazeh hatnufah
is, in general, the question is the גמרא Gemara's often talks about
the eating of the כהנים kohanim is like the eating of the
מזבח, Mizbe'ach, and the כהנים kohanim eat and the בעלים be'alim get
atonement. That's more stated by קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim where their eating
is done in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash itself, so therefore you
can see it like a type of an eating of the מזבח.
mizbe'ach The eating of קדשים קלים kodashim kalim of כהנים kohanim, too,
which is basically the חזה chazeh and שוק shok of the שלמים,
shlamim, they can eat in all of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you might say
that's not as much like eating of the מזבח. mizbe'ach And maybe
how do you conceive of when you're giving them the חזה chazeh
and the שוק? shok? Are you giving it to them like here's
a payment, you guys are working in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
here's some type of compensation? Or do you view it as like
giving it to God, but it's given to God and they happen
to be the ones working there so they're eating it sort of
like משלחן גבוה קזכו? mishulchan gavo'ah kazchu? It's always a question when
you give to the כהן, kohen? is it seen as a giving
to God or is it seen as a giving straight to the
כהן kohen. for their service? Sometimes the תורה Torah. says חלף עבודתם
אשר הם עובדים בעבודת אהל מועד, chelef avodatam asher hem ovdim ba'avodat
ohel moed, or is it that you give it to God and
the God gives it to the כהן? kohen So I think that
the idea of the חזה chazeh and שוק, shok, the reason it's
waved together with the fat is to make it more of a
giving to God. You wave it with the חלבים, chalavim, the חלבים
chalavim are going to the מזבח, mizbe'ach and therefore this is all
one bundle with the חלבים, chalavim, these are all the things that
you're giving to God from your שלמים. shlamim. So of that, the
חלבים chalavim go to the מזבח mizbe'ach and this goes to the
כהנים, kohanim. but presumably it's seen in the same way, it's seen
as part of that package and makes it more אכילה achilah of
the—אכילה achilah of the מזבח mizbe'ach or a giving to God rather
than a straight giving to the כהנים. kohanim Anyway, it is interesting
that you have it by שלמים, shlamim, you don't have it by
עולה, olah, you don't have it by other freewill sacrifices, you only
have it by שלמים shlamim and by both the part that goes
to the מזבח mizbe'ach. and the part that goes to the כהן.
kohen. Okay, so that's the שלמים, shlamim, that's in the תורה. Torah
אחד אנשים ואחד נשים, Echad anashim v'echad nashim,
whether men or women, even a woman's קרבן korban you do תנופה,
tnufa which now mention of women is significant because we know from
a פסוק pasuk. that or from a גמרא's Gemara's interpretation of a
פסוק pasuk that women don't do סמיכה, smicha, and here's another physical
act done with a קרבן, korban do women do it or not?
So here it says whether men or women, בישראל ולא באחרים, be-Yisrael
v'lo b'acherim, only by Jews and not by others. Now what does
that mean? Usually if it's contrasting ישראל Yisrael to אחרים, acherim, presumably
it means non-Jews. So it would mean maybe you don't do if
it's the קרבן korban of non-Jews. Men and women yes, but a
קרבן of non-Jews no. Especially given the last משנה mishna where we
spoke about מנחות of non-Jews that they get הגשה, so maybe here
it says but a קרבן of a non-Jew does not get תנופה.
tnufa. So that I would say is פשט pshat of the משנה,
mishna, but just wait because the גמרא's Gemara going to read it
in a different way. Okay. שתי הלחם ושני כבשי עצרת, Shtei halechem
u-shnei kivsei Atzeret,
and finally
the two loaves of שבועות Shavuot are waved, there's no הגשה as
we said before because none of it goes on the מזבח, mizbe'ach
and the two lambs, they're waved together with the two lambs, and
that's explicit in the תורה Torah that it says that they are
waved with the lambs of שבועות. Shavuot. כיצד הוא עושה? Keitzad hu
oseh? Now how do you physically do this? Sort of honing in
on the case of the שתי הלחם shtei halechem. because that's at
least the only מנחה of the list. So what do you do?
נותן שתי הלחם על גבי שני כבשים. Noten shtei halechem al gabei
shnei kvasim. You put the two loaves on the two lambs while
the lambs are alive. Actually, by here there's a waving that gets
done while the lambs are alive and then after the lambs are
slaughtered. Okay, so you put the two loaves on the two lambs
ומניח שתי ידיו למטה, u-maniach shtei yadav l'mata, and the כהן kohen?
puts his two hands underneath. And here it is a קרבן ציבור,
korban tzibbur, so the only player is the כהן. kohen. A lot
of these other pieces, the owner brings it, and the question is
who's doing the waving, the owner or the כהן? kohen The גמרא
Gemara will discuss that. But here it's a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibbur,
so the only person is the כהן. kohen He puts his two
hands underneath ומוליך ומביא מעלה ומוריד, u-molic u-meivi ma'aleh u-morid,
and he brings it forward and back, forward and back and up
and down, שנאמר, she'ne'emar, how do you now אשר הונף ואשר הורם
asher hunaf va'asher huram that was waved and lifted up, so we
understand that waving means somehow back and forth and הורם huram is
lifted up and down. Here's the, or really your question is if
your hands are underneath, right, how are you staying, how are you
keeping the lamb and the bread?
Yeah, that's the, that's the question if your hands have to be
totally underneath. Maybe you've got it bound up? And you've clamped the
bread for the lamb.
Yeah, that's the, that's the picture there, the whatever, the lamb, not
strapped but you're basically taking the, you sandwich it essentially. Uh-huh, and
then you know that there's like,
yeah,
I have a tiny dog. Dog.
I could not lift him with something on top of him and
move it, he wouldn't let me. And I'm talking about a tiny
dog.
Right, right.
A lamb's that big.
It's not,
I don't know, I don't know. Right, yeah, I don't know what
to do.
There's a thing of bread on top of it and it's going
to balance. Yeah.
Is
what we do with לולב Lulav related?
Yes, absolutely. And it's very good that you notice that, the לולב
Lulav is exactly the up and down, forward and back. And also
the גמרא Gemara. actually we'll see will connect it, uses a similar
phrasing that the waving of the לולב Lulav is because you know
סוכות Sukkot is during the beginning of the rainy period and it's
seen as a type of a prayer for the winds and the
rains. And that's also another more explicitly ties that in with תנופה
tnufa of the לולב. Lulav. And that's also how it ties it
in, you know, to some of these as well. We will get
at the end of today, the beginning of tomorrow, a whole discussion
of how the waving was done and what it symbolized. And yes,
there's direct parallels to the לולב. Lulav. So yes, let's keep that
in mind when we get to that. Okay, so it says like
this, okay, שנאמר, shene'emar, as it says אשר הונף ואשר הורם. asher
hunaf va'asher huram. תנופה היתה במזרח, tnufa hayeta bemizrach,
the waving could take place even in the east, right there, you
know at the beginning of the עזרה. Azarah. However, הגשה במערב, hagasha
bemarav, the touching to the מזבח mizbe'ach. was in the west. Why?
Because it says לפני ה', lifnei Hashem, right?
I want to remind you, you know the picture, but anyway, here
you walk in,
here, this is it, so you're walking in, right? This is where
the מזבח mizbe'ach. is, this is to the west, the קודש קדשים
Kodesh Kadashim is there. Okay, so the waving can be basically as
soon as I walk in, anywhere here. But the הגשה to the
מזבח, mizbe'ach there's two conditions that have to be satisfied. One, אל
פני המזבח, el pnei haMizbe'ach, the face of the מזבח. mizbe'ach So
the ramp is here, the face is here, so it has to
be somewhere in the south. This is the south. But it also
says לפני ה' על פני המזבח. lifnei Hashem al pnei haMizbe'ach. And
לפני ה' lifnei Hashem is understood as where the, you know, אולם
Ulam and the היכל Heichal is, like where the קודש Kodesh and
קודש קדשים Kodesh Kadashim are, right? Which is further westward. So both
פני המזבח pnei haMizbe'ach and לפני ה' lifnei Hashem is going to
be the southwest corner. Okay, so we'll talk about that more. But
anyway, the הגשה therefore was in the west, but the תנופה tenufah.
could be even in the east.
תנופה קודמת להגשות. tnufa kodemet lehagashot. Now, you first, if you have
a קרבן that you do both, we haven't even mentioned yet the
קרבן you do both, but it is going to be the עומר.
Omer, So first you do the waving and then you do the
הגשה. Okay, מנחת העומר ומנחת קנאות, minchat ha'Omer uminchat kna'ot, the
מנחה of the עומר Omer, and the מנחה for jealousy, for the
סוטה. טעונות הגשה, te'unot hagasha, you do הגשה as we said, those
are מנחות and they're burnt on the מזבח, mizbe'ach. part of them,
so you do הגשה. ותנופה, utnufa, and תנופה. tenufah, The תורה Torah...
actually says you do תנופה tenufah by these. So again, by the
עומר, Omer obviously there's a parallel to the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem.
You do the waving of the עומר, you do the waving of
the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem, What is the significance of that? Not
clear, but again as Seth indicates, there seems to be a series
of these תנופות tnufot that are associated around the agricultural symbolism. Right?
So you have the ביכורים Bikkurim according to one opinion, you have
the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem. you have the עומר, right? Which gets
you שבועות Shavuot and פסח. Pesach. And then the only thing you
don't have is סוכות. Sukkot. And then Seth reminds us you have
the waving of the לולב. Lulav. Okay, which is more חז"ל's Chazal
understanding, but presumably informed by this idea, trying to see that. So
somehow these wavings are types of, best understood like חז"ל Chazal understand
as types of prayers around concerns of, you know, a bountiful year
in the agriculture whether it's the rain or the ביכורים Bikkurim or
so on. So that's the, that is the issue about the עומר
and the שתי הלחם. That seems to be the common denominator. The
issue about the מנחת קנאות minchat kna'ot is harder to understand. Although
there I would make it more similar conceptually to the, what do
you call it, to like the מצורע. metzora. That there it's somehow
about designating this in the relationship to the person, to have it
be effective for the person. So the same way by the מצורע
metzora that was to be used in this ritual of טהרה, tahara,
by the סוטה it's somehow to be used in this ritual of
בירור עון. berur avon. Okay, but there seems to be very different
functions of the תנופה. tenufah Basically, we're just following the פסוקים psukim
here. Okay? So this is what the פסוקים say. So those two
get both.
לחם הפנים ומנחת נסכים. lechem hapanim uminchat nesachim. Now, לחם הפנים lechem
hapanim and the מנחת נסכים minchat nesachim אינן טעונות, einan te'unot, do
not require לא הגשה ולא תנופה. lo hagasha velo tnufa. Not הגשה
for the reason we said before, מנחת נסכים Minchat Nesachim. doesn't come
on its own, and the לחם הפנים none of it gets burnt
directly on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, and they don't get תנופה tenufah because
the תורה... Torah Never says תנופה. tenufah Okay. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi
Shimon omer, so that pretty much wraps it up. רבי שמעון now
makes a little summary statement, not exactly about what we've been talking
about, but related: ג׳ מינים טעונים ג׳ מצוות, gimmel minim te’unim gimmel
mitzvot, not מצות. matzot. Okay, there are three types of things that
between them, three of the following מצוות mitzvot will apply be applied,
but only will be two out of the three for any for
each one of them. שתים בכל אחת ואחת והשלישית אין בהן. shtayim
bechol achat ve’achat vehashlishit ein bahen. Every one of the three things
I'm going to mention get two מצוות mitzvot of three, but none
of them get all three. What's he talking about? Let's take a
look. ואלו הן, ve’elu hen, here are the three things I'm talking
about: זבחי שלמי יחיד, zivchei shalmei yachid, a שלמים shelamim of an
individual; וזבחי שלמי ציבור, vezivchei shalmei tzibbur, the שלמי shalmei sacrifice of
the ציבור, tzibbur, which is the two lambs of שבועות; Shavuot; ואשם
מצורע, ve’asham metzora, and the אשם asham of a מצורע. metzora. Those
are the three things. Now, here are the three מצוות mitzvot that
two of which apply to each one of them. Okay, זבחי שלמי
יחיד, zivchei shalmei yachid, the שלמים shelamim of an individual, טעונים סמיכה,
te’unim semichah, you do סמיכה semichah because you do סמיכה semichah on
personal קרבנות korbanot not on ציבור קרבנות, tzibbur korbanot, so you do
סמיכה semichah חיים chayim while the animal's alive, obviously that's when that's
the only time you do סמיכה, semichah, ותנופה שחוטים utenufah shechutim and
you wave it when they're dead. That's a שלמים shelamim like we
said, you wave the breast and the side and the and the
what do you call it and the fats. Okay, so שלמים shelamim
get סמיכה semichah and תנופה, tenufah that's two. Okay, the third one
that they don't get is תנופה tenufah when it's alive. So those
are the three things we're going to be looking at: סמיכה, semichah,
תנופה tenufah when it's dead, תנופה tenufah when it's alive. שלמים shelamim
only gets תנופה tenufah. when it's dead. ואין בהן תנופת חיים, ve’ein
bahen tenufat chayim, they don't get תנופה tenufah. when it's alive. זבחי
שלמי ציבור, zivchei shalmei tzibbur, the two lambs of שבועות, Shavuot, טעונים
תנופה, te’unim tenufah, get waved חיים chayim when they're alive, that we
said, ושחוטים u’shechutim and when they're dead. We haven't said that yet,
but that's the הלכה, halachah, they get waved alive and dead, two
different waving. ואין בהן סמיכה, ve’ein bahen semichah, there's no סמיכה semichah
because it's a communal sacrifice. ואשם מצורע, ve’asham metzora, the אשם asham
of a מצורע, metzora, טעון סמיכה, ta’un semichah, get סמיכה semichah because
it's personal sacrifice, ותנופה חי, utenufah chai, waving when it's alive, ואין
בו תנופה שחוט, ve’ein bo tenufah shechut, not תנופה tenufah, when it
is dead. Okay, so each one of these gets something different. Okay,
it's interesting also to speculate the significance of תנופה tenufah while it's
alive versus תנופה tenufah while it's dead. I haven't figured that out
yet. I'm still working on just תנופה. tenufah Okay, what is the
sort of what the logic is for certain things getting תנופה. tenufah,
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan,
so we have taught: והקריב, vehikriv, והקריב אותו לאשם, vehikriv oto le’asham,
we start with the מצורע, metzora, you shall bring it for an
אשם, asham, the lamb, ואת לוג השמן, ve’et log hashemen, the log
of
oil, והניף אותם, vehenif otam, תנופה, tenufah as a wave offering. מלמד
שטעונים תנופה, melamed shete’unim tenufah, it teaches that they get waved, כאחד,
ke’echad, as one, because there's wave them, presumably both of them at
the same זמן. zman. ומנין שהניף זה בעצמו וזה בעצמו יצא, uminayin
shehenif zeh be’atzmo vezeh be’atzmo yatza, how do you know that it's
good if you can even if you did one each one individually,
not together, it still works, which I would say is a pretty
big חידוש, chiddush, because who knows what the תנופה tenufa is doing?
Maybe the whole role of the תנופה tenufa is to designate the
oil as connected to the lamb, and maybe it's not effective when
it's not waved together with the lamb? Right, I mean if you
remember before when we had the loaves of עצרת Atzeret and the
כבשים of עצרת, Atzeret, and we
know you can still bring your לוג log afterwards.
Well by the מצורע, metzora, you can bring it by by מנחת
נסכים.
I think you can bring it individually.
You might be right, might be right. Anyway, but that's certainly, if
so, that would be part of the חידוש, chiddush, because sometimes you
could think that the whole point is to designate it together. So
how do you know if you bring one by itself and the
other by itself יצא, yatza, you fulfill your obligation? תלמוד לומר, talmud
lomar, והקריב אותו לאשם, vehikriv oto le’asham, והניף. vehenif. You sort of
put the period before you get to the אותם, otam, before you
get והניף אותם, vehenif otam, if you just said והניף, vehenif, period,
so it would mean you do even if you just did תנופה
tenufa on one of them, not really on one of them, but
on each of them separately, even that is good בדיעבד. bedi’avad. Now,
יכול יניף ויחזיר ויניף, yachol yanif veyachzir veyanif, maybe you should do
both? Maybe should wave them individually and then wave them also together?
תלמוד לומר, תנופה, tenufa a wave offering in the singular, ולא תנופות,
velo tenufot, not multiple ones. Okay, so from here we learn that
you're supposed to do it together, but based on this דרשה, drashah,
if you do it separately, it also works. And Mike might be
right, I think he is, I have to double check, but you
are? Okay, I think you are. From what I remember anyway, that
that's an even better example or whatever, further example of that they
don't need to be together is you might be able to bring
the לוג log even separately. I have to double check that, but
that also that does ring a bell. Okay, לפני ה׳, lifnei Hashem,
now you do this תנופה tenufa? before God, במזרח, bamizrach, in the
east. Now that's strange because normally לפני ה׳ lifnei Hashem means in
the west, closer to the קודש Kodesh and the קודש קדשים. Kodesh
Kodashim. So the גמרא Gemara says, that's what the גמרא Gemara says:
אמר לפני ה׳ יכול במערב? amar lifnei Hashem yachol bama’arav? For a
minute, it says before God, maybe it requires west, normally we say
before God requires west. So the גמרא Gemara says, and we say
it by the הגשה, we know the הגשה is at the west,
southwest corner, so it's both פני מזבח penei mizbe’ach and לפני ה׳,
lifnei Hashem, so west means לפני ה׳, lifnei Hashem, לפני ה׳ lifnei
Hashem means west. So אמרי הני מילי מנחה דאיקרי חטאת, amrei hanei
mili minchah de’ikri chatat, when do we say west means before God?
That's a מנחה that's a חטאת. chatat. Why? וחטאת טעונה יסוד, vechatat
te’unah yesod, and the חטאת chatat requires the
foundation, וקרן דרומית מזרחית לא היה לה יסוד. vekeren dromit mizrachit lo
hayah lah yesod. And the south and the and the southeast corner
did not have a יסוד. yesod. So we know it had to
be on the south face of the מזבח mizbe'ach. because it says
פני המזבח. p'nei hamizbe'ach. So if it has to be the south
part of the מזבח is it going to be southeast or southwest?
It can't be southeast because if you remember before the יסוד yesod
included this corner, this whole wall, this whole wall, this corner, but
it was not at this corner, not at the southeast corner. So
if it's going to be in the south and it can't be
at the southeast because it requires the יסוד yesod we're assuming it
had to be at the southwest. So what the גמרא Gemara is
actually saying is you know what לפני השם lifnei Hashem doesn't mean
West. לפני השם lifnei Hashem could even mean East. The reason it's
in the West is because we need the יסוד. yesod. Now that
leads תוספות Tosafot to have a big תוספות Tosafot that says what
are you talking about? Like there's so many times that we say
and there's other גמרות Gemorot that say by the מנחה that we
know it's at the West because it says לפני השם lifnei Hashem
and לפני השם lifnei Hashem means to the West closer to the
קודש קודשים. Kodesh Kodashim. So he doesn't really have a good answer.
This גמרא Gemara though is making that assertion that לפני השם lifnei
Hashem does not particularly mean West. The only way we know West
is because it requires a יסוד. yesod. It means in the עזרה,
Azara, although רש"י Rashi even says it is that because of the
reason it has to say לפני השם lifnei Hashem is אבל הכא
לפני השם קרינא ביה. aval hacha lifnei Hashem karina beih. By the
תנופה tenufa it says לפני השם lifnei Hashem because רש"י Rashi says
maybe I could have done the תנופה tenufa outside the מקדש, Mikdash,
right? If I'm מקריב makriv a קרבן outside the מקדש Mikdash and
I need the מנחה, I mean the other things I do outside
the מקדש, Mikdash, maybe I could do the תנופה tenufa? out of
the מקדש. Mikdash. So all לפני השם lifnei Hashem means is in
the מקדש, Mikdash, but it doesn't mean a specific place in the
מקדש Mikdash and the only way we know that is יסוד. yesod.
Again תוספות Tosafot is really you know disturbed by this because so
often we say לפני השם lifnei Hashem means to the West, but
here the גמרא Gemara is being more broad in what it means
to allow תנופה to be done everywhere. I do want to also
point out about the idea of הגשה. The idea that a הגשה
requires יסוד yesod is an interesting idea and emphasized why because it
is because you know because what requires יסוד? yesod? זריקת הדם zrikas
hadam can only take place at a corner that has the יסוד
yesod underneath it. That's normally the significance of the יסוד yesod that
the זריקת הדם can only be on the part of the מזבח
that has the יסוד yesod underneath it.
So the emphasis of a הגשת מנחה hagashtas mincha requiring a יסוד
yesod I think underscores the idea of looking at
הגשת מנחה hagashtas mincha as a type of a זריקת הדם of
the מנחה. It's the putting of the מנחה on the מזבח and
therefore the requirement of the יסוד. yesod.
You got a question Mordechai? This is wondering if פני השם pnei
Hashem could refer not just to a geographic location but also direction
orientation.
Oh you're facing that way as opposed to maybe. I mean here
we're sort of assuming you're right I mean you could sort of
have your back to it you know one's back to the מזבח
when you're I mean certainly you have that by the פרה אדומה
parah adumah you know you face towards the מזבח. I don't know
if it uses לפני השם lifnei Hashem there it says, but it
certainly speaks to that facing as important. Here the גמרא Gemara isn't
focusing on that. Okay so let's keep on going. But anyway what
I think is most significant about all this is that we learn
the importance of יסוד yesod for מנחה which again for the הגשה
of a מנחה which underscores that idea of a type of a
זריקה. zrika. Okay so now we continue. ביכורים כדברי רבי אלעזר בן
יעקב. bikkurim k'divrei Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov. ביכורים bikkurim like רבי אלעזר
בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov that says that you don't just
place it down you wave it. מאן רבי אלעזר בן יעקב? man
Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov? Who is this רבי אלעזר בן יעקב? Rabbi
Elazar ben Yaakov? דתניא detanya we learned in a ברייתא. braisa. ולקח
הכהן. v'lakach hacohen.
The כהן kohen. shall take the basket from your hand. Right? Let's
let me just read that פסוק pasuk because it says והנחתו v'hinnachto
twice in that פסוק. pasuk.
So here it is כי תבוא. Ki Savo.
ולקחתם מראשית כל פרי האדמה v'lakachtam m'reishis kol pri
ha'adamah etc.
you bring it to the כהן kohen, ואמרת אליו הגדתי היום לה'
אלקיך כי באתי אל הארץ אשר נשבע ה' לאבתינו לתת לנו. v'amarta
eilav higadti hayom l'Hashem Elokecha ki vasi el ha'aretz asher nishba Hashem
la'avoseinu lases lanu. ולקח הכהן הטנא מידך. v'lakach hacohen hatene miyadecha.
He takes it from your hand. והניחו לפני מזבח ה' אלקיך v'hinnicho
lifnei mizbach Hashem Elokecha in front of the מזבח of the Lord
your God. Then וענית ואמרת v'anisa v'amarta you say the whole ארמי
אובד אבי Arami oveid avi etc. etc. and at the end of
the whole thing ועתה הנה הבאתי את ראשית פרי האדמה v'ata hinei
heiveisi es reishis pri ha'adamah I've
given my first of the first fruit of the first אשר נתתה
לי ה'. asher nasata li Hashem. והנחתו לפני ה' אלקיך והשתחוית לפני
ה' אלקיך. v'hinnachto lifnei Hashem Elokecha v'hishtachavita lifnei Hashem Elokecha. You shall
leave it before the Lord your God and you go and you
bow down. Meaning it was already placed there by the כהן. kohen
You leave it there, you bow down, and then afterwards the כהנים
kohanim take it and they're going to eat it. Okay but you
have presented it. Now by the way I should say because it
does tie into the whole idea that we talked about you know
כל שאור וכל דבש לא תקטירו ממנו אשה לה'. kol se'or v'chol
devash lo saktiru mimenu isheh l'Hashem. על המזבח לא יעלו. al hamizbe'ach
lo ya'alu. You don't put שאור se'or and דבש devash on the
מזבח. What do you do? קרבן ראשית תקריבו אתם. korban reishis takrivu
osam. So here you are actually putting it right והנחתו לפני מזבח
ה' אלקיך. v'hinnachto lifnei mizbach Hashem Elokecha.
You're putting it right there by the מזבח. You're walking away. So
from your experience it's sort of like they went on the מזבח
right? You put them there you didn't see anything else happen you
put them nearby you left. Then the כהנים will take it and
eat it. So they don't go on the מזבח but they get
pretty close. Okay so that's what the תורה Torah. says about the
ביכורים. bikkurim. Now where are we going to try to read into
these words והנחתו v'hinnachto or והניחו v'hinnicho
a type of a תנופה? Let's take a look. Okay דתניא detanya
רבי אלעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov. ויאמר על ביכורים שטעונין
תנופה. v'omar al bikkurim shete'unin tenufa.
The ביכורים bikkurim get waved. דברי רבי אלעזר בן יעקב. divrei Rabbi
Elazar ben Yaakov. מאי טעמא דרבי אלעזר בן יעקב? mai ta'ama d'Rabbi
Elazar ben Yaakov? Where does he get that from? גמר יד יד
משלמים בגזירה שוה. gamar yad yad mishlamim b'gezeira shava. כתיב הכא ולקח.
ksiv hacha v'lakach. ולקח הכהן הטנא מידך v'lakach hakohen et hatene miyadecha
from your hand, וכתיב התם u'ktiv hatam and it says by the
שלמים, shlamim, ידיו תביאנה yadav tvi'enu your hand shall bring it and
it says and therefore it says your hands bring the שלמים shlamim
and you take the חזה ושוק chaze v'shok and you wave them.
מה כאן כהן אף להלן כהן. ma kan kohen af lehalan kohen.
Now, we also learned not only do you get waving, but we
also learn who the players are. So the same way there it
says by the ביכורים bikkurim it says you give it to the
כהן, kohen. so the כהן kohen obviously is a major player. So
when it talks about you're waving the חזה chaze and the שוק
shok of the שלמים, shlamim, it's also not by yourself but with
the כהן. kohen. ומה להלן בעלים u'mah lehalan ba'alim but the same
way there it's more clear that you're bringing the חזה ושוק chaze
v'shok and you're waving it, so אף כאן בעלים af kan ba'alim
even the waving of the ביכורים bikkurim is with the owner. So
we take the גזירה שווה, gzerah shavah, we assume there's waving of
ביכורים bikkurim and now we have said that these two wavings involve
both the כהן kohen and the owners. It's an interesting question which
conceptually is the primary person, the owner or the כהן. kohen We'll
see about that in a little bit. הא כיצד, ha keitzad, how
does this mean? How does this take place? כהן מניח ידו תחת
ידי בעלים ומניף. kohen maniach yado tachat yedei ba'alim u'manif. The כהן
kohen puts his hands under the owner's hands and you wave. Now,
the fact that the כהן's kohen hands are underneath, I would say
suggests conceptually that the owners are the primary wavers and bringers, which
makes sense. Your שלמים, shlamim, your ביכורים, bikkurim, you're the primary one
waving, but together with the כהן kohen maybe because it's in the
process of being given over to the כהן kohen whether it's the
ביכורים bikkurim or whether it's the שלמים. shlamim. תוספות Tosafot has a
whole discussion whether it literally means the כהן's kohen. hands are underneath
yours. He has a problem of חציצה. chatzitza. And תוספות Tosafot suggests
that what it could be, the כהן's kohen hands are not touching
the basket. Okay, presumably if you need that, if normal עבודה avodah
need things to be in contact directly. So תוספות Tosafot says maybe
what it means underneath is not underneath your hands. Maybe it means
that your hands are holding the top of the basket, sorry, your
hands are holding the top of the basket, and his hands are
holding the bottom of the basket, the כהן. kohen That way, if
that's what it's saying, then it's less clear who's the primary, who's
secondary. He quotes from ירושלמי Yerushalmi not that way because ירושלמי Yerushalmi
have a whole problem about the תנופה of the מנחת סוטה that
isn't the... how can the כהן kohen be touching a woman's hands
and what about, you know, הרהורם hirhuram or whatever, oh, it's only
for a few seconds, there's not going to be הרהורם hirhuram during
that time. Anyway, from that ירושלמי Yerushalmi it sounds like he was
literally underneath the hands. Also, it does raise the possible reason which
we're going to see in a minute about the problematic from the
גמרא's Gemara perspective of the idea of a woman doing תנופה if
the hands were touching one another. So we'll get to that.
Why doesn't a woman do תנופה?
If you understand that the כהן's hands are underneath and you understand
there's a problem for a man to be touching a woman's hands
even in that process, the גמרא Gemara might have problems with that
idea. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi had problems with that idea by סוטה.
Okay. What if a woman's standing in during...
no, she'd be standing in the עזרה. azarah. A woman can go
into the עזרה. azarah. Okay, so let's just finish this up. So
anyway, that's תוספות's Tosafot point about how it's underneath. Now, ולימא כדברי
רבי יהודה, u'leima k'divrei Rabbi Yehuda, why don't we just say it's
רבי אלעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov, why not say it's
רבי יהודה? How do you know רבי יהודה also says that the
owners, that there's waving by the ביכורים? bikkurim? דתניא, d'tanya, we turn
a ברייתא, braita, רבי יהודה אומר והנחתו זו תנופה, Rabbi Yehuda omer
v'hinachto zu tenufa, you shall place it,
that means waving. אתה אומר זו תנופה או אינו אלא הנחה, ata
omer zu tenufa o eino ela hanacha, maybe it literally means leave
your ביכורים, bikkurim, which is what it sounds like in the תורה.
Torah כשהוא אומר והניחו, keshehu omer v'hinicho, no, because it already said
the כהן placed the ביכורים bikkurim by the מזבח. Why does it
say at the end you shall leave it? Now obviously it's different.
One is he's placing it and you're doing the whole declaration in
front of the ביכורים bikkurim and then the next is you walk
out of the door, you leave it where it is, you don't
take it with you and you walk out of the door. But
anyway, why does it repeat it? הרי הנחה אמורה, harei hanacha amura,
we've already mentioned placement. הא מה אני מקיים והנחתו, ha ma ani
mekayem v'hinachto, how do I fulfill you shall leave it? זו תנופה,
zu tenufa, it's the waving. Now, by the way, there's a difference.
When did you do the waving? Did you do the waving before
or after you did the declaration? If we learn it out from
והנחתו, v'hinachto, right, which is after the whole declaration, presumably you did
the waving after you declared. If you learned it out from the
פסוק about ידיו, yadav, you know, you bring it to from your
hand, so that suggests the idea that the waving occurred at the
beginning. And the גמרא before quoted the
פסוק about ולקח הכהן מן ידך. v'lakach hakohen miyadecha. Anyway, so why
couldn't we say our משנה mishnah is also רבי יהודה? אמר רבא,
amar Rava, so רבא Rava says הואיל ופתח בו כתוב תחילה. ho'il
u'patach bo katuv techila. We'd rather say רבי אלעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi
Elazar ben Yaakov, sorry about all that, we'd rather say רבי אלעזר
בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov because רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi
Elazar ben Yaakov learns from an earlier part of the פסוק. He
learns from ולקח הכהן הטנא מידך, v'lakach hakohen et hatene miyadecha, which
is earlier than the והנחתו. v'hinachto. אוי, oy, as I said before,
not only is it earlier, but it's also might have
also indicated that the waving takes place earlier in the process before
the declaration, which by the way, you know, there's something nice about
that model that you're waving. It's funny in the תורה if you
admit it. Like what? I bring my ביכורים bikkurim and I just
leave it there? I don't do anything with it? It doesn't go
on the מזבח, you know, there's no offering up, I just give
it and I leave it there, put it down near the מזבח.
So you sort of can understand the idea that you do this
whole ritual of giving, of waving makes a lot of sense. Anyway,
רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר הואיל ורב גברא, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
amar ho'il v'rav gavra, because רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben
Yaakov is a... Strength is great. Meaning we very often rule like
רב אלעזר בן יעקב, Rav Elazar ben Yaakov, we say הלכה halacha
רב אלעזר בן יעקב Rav Elazar ben Yaakov משנתו קב ונקי, mishnaso
kav venaki, so therefore yes it could have said רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda but we'd rather say it's going according to רב אליעזר בן
יעקב. Rav Eliezer ben Yaakov. Okay. And here for today.